Guide to the W. J. Linton Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
W. J. Linton Collection
1797-1937
1838-1897
GEN MSS 1387
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
16.43
21 boxes
The collection consists of the papers of author and wood engraver W. J. Linton, including personal and professional correspondence, writings by and about Linton, drawings and prints, personal papers, and other papers covering Linton's life and work in England and the United States. The papers are primarily those inherited by his daughters Ellen Wade Linton and Margaret Linton Mather, with additions from family friends.
Linton, W. J. (William James), 1812-1897
Gifford, R. Swain (Robert Swain), 1840-1905
Gillray, James, 1756-1815
Landor, Walter Savage, 1775-1864
Sibson, Thomas, 1817-1844
Stoddard, Richard Henry, 1825-1903
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired chiefly through gifts of Margaret Linton Mather, 1911-1929, and Ellen Wade Linton, 1918. Additional gifts from William Fowler Hopson and Ada M. Hopson, 1918-1920; Alfred E. Hamill (Yale 1905), 1928-1929; and Howard Mansfield (Yale 1871, MA Hon 1891), 1929. Other acquistions are noted at the folder level in the finding aid. For additional information, consult the appropriate curator.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Correspondence, 1829-1931. II. Writings by Linton, 1845-1898. III. Writings about Linton, 1839-1937. IV. Graphic Material, 1838-1913. V. Personal Papers, 1838-1902. VI. Other Papers, 1797-1922.
W. J. Linton (1812-1897)
The British wood engraver, author, historian, printer, publisher, and political activist William James Linton was born in London on December 7, 1812. He immigrated to New York in 1866 and in 1867 settled at Appledore, a small farm and cottage in Hamden, Connecticut, just north of New Haven. There he founded his Appledore Private Press and wrote and printed several of his most notable works including The Masters of Wood-Engraving (1886). Linton died in New Haven, at the home of his daughter Margaret Linton Mather, on December 29, 1897.
Associated Materials
Grace Linton Cook Papers About W. J. Linton (GEN MSS 1406), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Scope and Contents
The W. J. Linton Collection chiefly contains William James Linton's papers, including correspondence, autograph manuscripts and other writings by and about Linton, graphic work, and personal papers, which were inherited by his daughters Ellen Wade Linton and Margaret Linton Mather, when their father died in New Haven, Connecticut, in 1897. It includes literary and graphic material that Linton brought with him when he emigrated from England to the United States in the mid-1860s, as well as work he accomplished while living in Connecticut. Once the papers entered the Yale University Library beginning in 1911, they were added through 1929 by family members and by gifts from three local admirers of Linton who were also friends of the family: the engraver William Fowler Hopson and two Yale graduates, Howard Mansfield and Alfred E. Hamill. These substantial gifts combine to comprise the largest group of Linton's autograph literary manuscripts, examples of engravings and other printed work he created both in England and the United States, and material related to Linton's classic works The History of Wood Engraving in America (1882) and Masters of Wood Engraving (1886).
Chartism; Wood-engravers -- Great Britain; Wood-engravers -- United States; Wood-engraving -- 19th century; Etchings (prints) -- Great Britain -- 18th century; Etchings (prints) -- United States -- 19th century; Oil paintings (visual works) -- 19th century; Photographs -- United States -- 19th century; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Wood engravings (prints) -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Wood engravings (prints) -- United States -- 19th century; Wood-engravers -- Great Britain -- 19th century; Wood-engravers -- United States -- 19th century; Ayton, Richard, 1786-1823; Beatty, Pakenham (Pakenham William Hengist Albert Mazzini), 1855-1930; Crane, Walter, 1845-1915; Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1803-1882; Foote, Mary Hallock, 1847-1938; Forman, H. Buxton (Harry Buxton), 1842-1917; Gifford, R. Swain (Robert Swain), 1840-1905; Gillray, James, 1756-1815; Hinton, Richard J. (Richard Josiah), 1830-1901; Hunt, Thornton Leigh, 1810-1873; Jones, Ebenezer, 1820-1860; Landor, Walter Savage, 1775-1864; Larken, Edmund Roberts, 1809-1895; Linton, W. J. (William James), 1812-1897; Lossing, Benson John, 1813-1891; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872; Munby, Arthur Joseph, 1828-1910; Newman, Francis William, 1805-1897; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900; Sibson, Thomas, 1817-1844; Shepherd, Richard Herne, 1842-1895; Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1833-1908; Stoddard, Richard Henry, 1825-1903; Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874; Swinburne, Algernon Charles, 1837-1909; Watson, James, 1799-1874; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Winter, William, 1836-1917; Worcell, Stanisław Gabriel, 1799-1857; Central Committee of the Friends of Poland; Walthamstow Working Men's Association
- Correspondence, 1829–1931; Series I; 0.84; 2 boxes
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into three subseries: Letters to Linton, Letters from Linton, and Third-party Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  The series primarily contains single letters from friends and colleagues and many of whom are engravers or family members of engravers writing in reply to Linton's inquiries about the profession and history of wood engraving, as well as from others, such as the artist William Page who wrote to praise Linton for his fine work in reproducing one of his paintings. Another prominent group of correspondents are those asking for permission to use Linton's poems in anthologies, while two poets, Walter Savage Landor and Richard Henry Stoddard, wrote to send poems they had written about Linton. High-profile correspondents include Ralph Waldo Emerson (writing about an oil portrait of himself by David Scott that Linton was engraving), William Morris, John Ruskin (writing about Brantwood, Linton's home that Ruskin acquired when Linton moved to the United States), and Walt Whitman. Several of the letters in the series are related to Linton's work with Guiseppe Mazzini and the Central Committee of the Friends of Poland. The subseries Letters from Linton holds an interesting set of letters to H. W. Thompson giving him instructions for the dispersal and disposal of papers Linton had left behind in England. The subseries Third-party Correspondence holds a small group of letters that others, including family members, wrote or received about Linton and his work.
  - Letters to Linton
    - Adams, Joseph Alexander, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Adams, Sarah Flower, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Allingham, William, 1883 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Andrew, George T., 1879 August 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Enclosing a short biography of his father, the engraver John Andrew.
    - Anthony, A. V. S. (Andrew Varick Stout), 1876-1879, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Avery, Mary Ann Ogden, 1896 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Balewski, Louis, 1869 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Letter in French.
    - Bamberger, Ludwig, 1851 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bates, Arlo, 1887 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Bergson, Edward W., 1889 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - British Museum, 1852 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Acknowledgement for copy of his The English Republic given to the museum.
    - Browning, Robert, 1883 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bryant, William Cullen, 1870 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Buchanan, Robert Williams, 1883 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Bullen, A. H. (Arthur Henry), 1891, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Burling, Gilbert, 1861 February 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Regarding Linton's election to the American Society of Painters in Water Colors (later American Watercolor Society).
    - Carlyle, Thomas, 1861 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Carnegie, Andrew, [1893?] (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Chapin, John Reuben, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Regarding Alexander Anderson and other engravers.
    - Cheney, Ednah Dow, 1870 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Concerning David Scott's portrait of Ralph Waldo Emerson.
    - Cole, Charles Augustus, 1882 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Cole, Timothy, 1879 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Colvin, Sidney, 1895 June 15 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Cooper, Thomas, 1853 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      On verso of the fourth sheet of the letter: Linton's undated autograph poem "Arbitration: a question"
    - Cooper Union for the Advancement of Science and Art, 1867, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Letters from Abram S. Hewitt, secretary, regarding Linton's appointment as director of engraving at the Cooper Union's Female Art Department.
    - Cowen, Joseph, 1891 August 27 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Crane, Walter, 1886–1896 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Darley, Felix Octavius Carr, 1879, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Davies, William, 1883 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Davis, John Parker, 1879 November 14 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Delescluze, Henri, 1871 September 7 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Letter in French concerning the work of his brother, Charles Delescluze.
    - DeVinne, Theodore Low, 1896 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Dobell, Emily, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Dobson, Austin, 1886–1887 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Duffy, Charles Gavan, Sir, 1884, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Dwight, Theodore F., 1878 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Ellwanger, George H. (George Herman), 1896 March 23 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Emerson, Ralph Waldo, 1869 September 21 (Box 1, Folder 38)
      Regarding the portrait of Emerson by David Scott; with three typed transcriptions
    - Farnum, Alexander, 1879 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Farrington, C. S., 1894 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Regarding the American Society of Engravers
    - Fechter, Charles, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Field, Kate, 1868 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Firth, C. H. (Charles Harding), 1894, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Foote, Mary Hallock, 1887, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Forman, H. Buxton (Harry Buxton), 1882 (Box 1, Folder 45)
      With an addendum note to "Mrs. Watson."
    - Forster, John, 1856 February 4 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Forster, W. E. (William Edward), 1866 October 5 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Foxton, Frederick Joseph, 1854 January 3 (Box 1, Folder 48)
      Thanking Linton for sending The English Republic.
    - Garfield, James A. (James Abram), 1869 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 49)
      Regarding a Joint Resolution expressing sympathy with the Republicans of Spain.
    - Garnett, Richard, 1895 June 7 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Gosse, Edmund, 1883 October 29 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Graul, Richard, 1888 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 52)
      Letter in French, enclosing autograph review by S. R. (Sylvester Rosa) Koehler of Linton's History of Wood Engraving (review in English).
    - Grossart, Alexander Balloch, 1873, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Hinton, Richard J. (Richard Josiah), 1869–1895 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Holcomb, Alfred G., 1867 February 9 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Horne, R. H. (Richard H.), 1875–1882 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Howe, Henry, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Howitt, Mary (Mary Botham), undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Huntington, Daniel, 1878 June 27 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Ingelow, Jean, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Jones, Sumner, 1877, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 61)
      Two letters concerning his brother Eben Jones, one to Linton and a copy of one to Horace Harral.
    - Karst, John, 1879 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Kossuth, Lajos, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - La Farge, John, 1875, undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Landor, Walter Savage, 1852–1858 (Box 1, Folder 65)
      Three letters and two copies of his poem "To the Author of the Plaint of Freedom," plus one copy of the poem clipped from The Examiner (July 23, 1853).
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      1852 letter removed from Landor's The Last Fruit Off an Old Tree (London: Edward Moxon, 1853).
    - Lindsay, Thomas M. (Thomas Martin), 1884 January 8 (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Locker-Lampson, Frederick, 1883 April 10 (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Lossing, Benson John, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Lovejoy, E. Felix, 1853 February 14 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - MacDonald, George, 1883 November 12 (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Mackail, J. W. (John William), 1883 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Mackay, Charles, undated (Box 1, Folder 72)
      Signature torn from his letter to Linton.
    - Macready, William Charles, 1863 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 73)
      Concerning the Friends of Poland.
    - Marzials, Theophilus, 1872, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1853–1869 (Box 1, Folder 75)
      Eleven letters to Linton, one letter from Mazzini to E. A. Stansbury introducing Linton; also present: Mazzini's undated autograph manuscript of a proclamation to the Swiss, an 1853 postal receipt for the Central Committee of the Friends of Poland, and an 1861 receipt issued by the Garibaldi Special Fund Committee for a train ticket.
    - Mill, John Stuart, 1867, undated (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Modjeska, Helena, 1888 January 20 (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Morris, William, 1883 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Munby, Arthur Joseph, 1883–1894 (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - New Haven Free Public Library, 1893, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Newman, Francis William, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Newman, John Henry, 1883 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Nichol, John, 1883 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Nichols, D. (David), 1879 July 3 (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Nimmo, John C., 1889 March 29 (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - O'Brien, Robert, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 86)
      Includes one letter from O'Brien to Edward C. Herrick, discussing the career of Benjamin F. Childs (1814-1863).
    - Page, William, 1872–1873 (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Parkes, Kineton, 1896 September 5 (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Phillips, Wendell, undated (Box 1, Folder 89)
      Includes a letter by Phillips to D. R. Sheridan, introducing Linton.
    - Players (Club), 1894 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 90)
      Thanking Linton for his donation of "five pictures of Edwin Booth."
    - Polish Managing Committee, 1844 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 91)
      Letter to W. Lovett, W. J. Linton, J. H. Parry. H. Vincent, P. Taylor, and J. Watson.
    - Polish National Central Provisional Government, 1861 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Prang, Louis, 1896 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 93)
    - Procter, Anne Benson, undated (Box 1, Folder 94)
    - Pumpelly, Raphael, 1871 April 24 (Box 1, Folder 95)
    - Putnam, John Bishop, 1879 November 20 (Box 2, Folder 96)
    - Richards, T. Addison (Thomas Addison), 1879–1900 (Box 2, Folder 97)
    - Ritchie, Anne Thackeray, 1883 November 6 (Box 2, Folder 98)
    - Rossetti, William Michael, 1883 October 30 (Box 2, Folder 99)
    - Ruskin, John, 1871, undated (Box 2, Folder 100)
      One letter regarding his purchase of Brantwood.
    - Salt, Henry S., 1892 (Box 2, Folder 101)
      Requesting permission to use Linton's poems in a volume he is editing.
    - Sargent, John T. (John Turner), 1868 November 14 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    - Scott, William Bell, 1855, 1870 (Box 2, Folder 103)
      See also Walt Whitman, Box 2, folder 118.
    - Sharpe, Lancelot, 1837 December 13 (Box 2, Folder 104)
    - Stedman, Edmund Clarence, 1874–1895 (Box 2, Folder 105)
    - Stewart, R. H., undated (Box 2, Folder 106)
    - Stimson, Daniel M., 1897 May 26 (Box 2, Folder 107)
    - Stoddard, Richard Henry, 1892–1898 (Box 2, Folder 108)
      Includes two poems written by Stoddard about Linton.
    - Strong, Thomas W., 1879 December 18 (Box 2, Folder 109)
    - Sumner, Charles, 1871 January 27 (Box 2, Folder 110)
    - Swinburne, Algernon Charles, 1880–1883 (Box 2, Folder 111)
    - Thackeray, William Makepeace, undated (Box 2, Folder 112)
      Envelope only.
    - Thayer, William Roscoe, 1893, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 113)
    - Thomas, William Luson, 1896 November 7 (Box 2, Folder 114)
    - Thompson, H. W., 1896 October 13 (Box 2, Folder 115)
      Includes a transcript from a letter to B. F. Stevens to Kineton Parkes regarding his Linton bibliography.
    - Thompson, T. Perronet (Thomas Perronet), 1867 September 2 (Box 2, Folder 116)
    - Wellington, 1860 September 7 (Box 2, Folder 117)
      Regarding General Garibaldi's plans.
    - Whitman, Walt, 1872–1888 (Box 2, Folder 118)
      Includes a letter to Moncure D. Conway from William Bell Scott mentioning Linton and Whitman, which Whitman reused to write to Linton.
    - Whitney, A. D. T. (Adeline Dutton Train), undated (Box 2, Folder 119)
    - Whitney, Elias James, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 120)
    - Whittier, John Greenleaf, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 121)
    - Winter, William, 1870–1898 (Box 2, Folder 122)
    - Worcell, Stanisław Gabriel, 1856 January 14 (Box 2, Folder 123)
      Includes a manuscript copy of Mazzini's letter in French addressed to members of the Central Committee of the Friends of Poland, dated July 25, 1855.
    - Yale University, 1891 July 6 (Box 2, Folder 124)
      Letter from Franklin Bowditch Dexter, regarding Linton's honorary degree.
    - Yale University Library, 1885–1896 (Box 2, Folder 125)
      Acknowledgements for books given to the library.
  - Letters from Linton
    - Armour, George A., 1896 March 30 (Box 2, Folder 126)
    - Beatty, Pakenham (Pakenham William Hengist Albert Mazzini), 1881–1884 (Box 2, Folder 127)
      Seventeen letters.
      Purchased from Stanley Smith on the William Robertson Coe American Studies Fund, 1963.
    - Central Committee of the Friends of Poland, London, 1863 February 28 (Box 2, Folder 128)
      Contains letter written by Linton on behalf of the committee, and a copy of the committee's articles of organization.
    - Civil Service Review (editor), 1875 September 21 (Box 2, Folder 129)
    - Farnum, Alexander, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 130)
    - Forman, H. Buxton (Harry Buxton), 1875–1883 (Box 2, Folder 131)
      Letter of October 27, 1877, removed from Studies of Sensation and Event, by Ebenezer Jones (BEIN 2005 1674); gift of Mr. and Mrs. William Fowler Hopson, 1932.
    - Horne, R. H. (Richard H.), 1876 (Box 2, Folder 132)
    - Hunt, Thornton Leigh, 1849–1850 (Box 2, Folder 133)
    - Larken, Edmund Roberts, undated (Box 2, Folder 134)
      Laid in one letter: Linton's autograph manuscript of "the exposition of our principles."
    - London Quarterly Review (editor), 1879 April 30 (Box 2, Folder 135)
    - Lott, Mr., 1883 November 1 (Box 2, Folder 136)
      Removed from Claribel and Other Poems (BEIN 2005 1165).
    - Shepherd, Richard Herne, 1878–1879 (Box 2, Folder 137)
      Purchased from Quaritch on the Class of 1884, Yale College, Fund, 1962.
    - Stedman, Edmund Clarence, undated (Box 2, Folder 138)
    - Thompson, H. W., 1892–1893 (Box 2, Folder 139)
      Thirteen letters in which Linton gives instructions to Thompson regarding the dispersal and disposal of his papers and books in England.
      Purchased from W. A. Myers on the Library Associates Fund, 1966.
    - Way & Williams, 1896 February 25 (Box 2, Folder 140)
    - Winchell, Alverd E., 1896 March 24 (Box 2, Folder 141)
      Removed from Linton's Love-Lore and Other, Early and Late Poems (BEIN Z78 75); gift of Mr. and Mrs. William Fowler Hopson, 1932.
    - Winter, William, 1879 May 13 (Box 2, Folder 142)
      Concerning Linton's desire to have a musical produced. Accompanied by a copy of his Voices of the Dead: Charlotte Corday and Marat, Mazzini and the Countess Ossoli, Delescluze on the Barricade (1879).
    - Yale University Library, 1890-1896, undated (Box 2, Folder 143)
      Letters to Addison Van Name regarding Linton's donations to the library; accompanied by a manuscript list of books on library stationery.
      Two letters removed from University Librarian's correspondence files; one letter removed from Linton's Broadway Ballads (BEIN Z78 76).
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 2, Folder 144)
      Fragment of a letter.
  - Third-party Correspondence
    - Atwater, May, to William Fowler Hopson, 1931 June 14 (Box 2, Folder 145)
      Regarding "Appledore," Linton's home in Hamden, Connecticut
    - Linton, Ellen Wade to William Fowler Hopson, 1929 July 20 (Box 2, Folder 146)
    - Linton, Ellen Wade to Andrew Keogh, Yale University Library, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 147)
      Enclosing a copy of Walter Savage Landor's poem "To the Author of The Plaint of Freedom " for insertion into the Yale Library's copy of that book; with a typed carbon of Keogh's response.
    - North, Ernest Dressel to William Fowler Hopson, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 148)
      Regarding a Linton letter.
      Removed from Studies of Sensation and Event, by Ebenezer Jones (BEIN 2005 1674); gift of Mr. and Mrs. William Fowler Hopson, 1932.
    - Linton, William Wade to H. Buxton Forman, 1876–1878 (Box 2, Folder 149)
    - Stevens, Benjamin Franklin to R. Wagner, 1889 March 18 (Box 2, Folder 150)
      In German; requesting a print for Linton's Masters of Wood Engraving.
- Writings by Linton, 1845–1898; Series II; 4.38; 8 boxes
  The series contains a mix of bound volumes compiled by Linton, autograph manuscripts (many of which were written on the versos of stacks of Universal Republican Alliance subscription coupons), and printed items including tear sheets with published essays and poems.
  All works are autograph manuscripts, some with corrections, unless otherwise noted.
  Series two is organized into six subseries: Bound Compilations, Essays, Lectures, Poems, Prospectuses, and Other Writings.
  - Bound Compilations
    A group of bound thematic compilations created by Linton. Many of the writings appear to have come from The English Republic, edited by Linton and published in London 1851-1855. Titles are taken from their hand-lettered spines.
    - "Essays and Reviews from The English Republic ", undated (Box 3, Folder 151)
    - "Ket's Rebellion" ("The Rebellion of Ket the Tanner"), undated (Box 3, Folder 152)
      Five chapters as they originally appeared in The English Republic 3 (1854), collected to form a continuous narrative.
    - "Heroes and Martyrs", undated (Box 3, Folder 153)
    - "Republican Principles", undated (Box 3, Folder 154)
    - "Rhymes and Reasons Against Landlordism", undated (Box 3, Folder 155)
      Most published in the Irish Nation in the 1840s.
    - "Theodore Parker on The Christian Religion, Atheism and Theism…abridged by W. J. Linton", undated (Box 3, Folder 156)
    - "Twenty Essays Concerning Principles"
      - "Part 1: Moral and Religious" and "Part 2: Religious and Political", undated (Box 3, Folder 157)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3, Folder 158)
    - "Prose and Verse by W. J. Linton, a supplement to 1886", 1887–1897 (Box 3, Folder 159)
      Compilation of essays, poems, and letters to editors clipped from publications, with small Appledore Press folders and pamphlets, mounted on blank pages; printed title page and table of contents.
    - "Articles written on W. J. Linton and others", 1879–1898 (Box 3, Folder 160)
      Not related to the above volumes. Contains articles by Linton on James Watson, Joseph Mazzini, European Republicans, Chartists, and engraving, and about Linton by Frederick G. Kitton and Burton J. Hendrick, clipped from publications; also one on John Ruskin by Anne Thackeray Ritchie, which features a section on Brantwood. The volume was owned by Ellen Wade Linton (1852-1938). Laid in: postcard from Ellen Linton to Ada M. Hopson (1916).
  - Essays
    Additional essays appear in "Other Writings," including essay-length letters to editors printed in publications.
    - "The American Odyssey: Adventures of Ulysses"; 24 p., 1876 (Box 4, Folder 161)